Guide to the David Pass papers, 1934-2001
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
David Pass papers
1934-2001
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
David Pass, 1938-2007
C0037
17 linear feet 35 boxes
The David Pass papers contain correspondence, oral histories, research files, photographs, maps, and plans that document the development and study of new towns in the United States and internationally, particularly Sweden. The collection thoroughly documents Pass's career at the Royal Institute of Technology in Stockholm, Sweden, the Urban Development Corporation in New York, and the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development in Washington, D.C. Although the inclusive dates span from 1934 to 2001, the bulk of the collection dates from the early 1960s to the early 1980s.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by the estate of David Pass, July 25, 2008.
Biographical Information
David Pass was born on January 14, 1938 in Paterson, New Jersey and graduated from Stuyvesant High School in 1954. Pass earned a bachelor's from Columbia University in New York in 1958, a master's from the Architecture School in 1962, a B.S. from the Engineering School in 1964, a master's in city planning from University of California in Berkeley (also in 1964) and the equivalent of a Ph.D. in city planning from the Royal Institute of Technology in Stockholm in 1969. During his years as a student, he worked primarily as a planner for both public and private organizations in New York, Sweden, and California. From 1964-1969, he worked in the Royal Institute of Technology as the project director and chief researcher on "Vallingby and Farsta: The Suburban Development process in a Large Swedish City", which was later published as a book by MIT Press. Following his work in Sweden, he returned to the United States to work as the Director of New Communities and Environmental Quality in the New York State Urban Development Corporation. A career employee of HUD from 1973 until his 2003 retirement, Pass worked as the Senior Financial and Economic Advisor in the New Community Development Corporation and then later in Indian Affairs. In addition to writing "Vallingby and Farsta from Idea to Reality: the New Community Development Process in Stockholm" (1973), he also wrote "New Communities in New York State" (1971) and many other articles on new towns in Sweden and the United States. He died in Bethesda, Maryland on July 18, 2007.
Scope and Content
The David Pass papers contain correspondence, oral histories, research files, photographs, maps, and plans that document the development and study of new towns in the United States and internationally, particularly Sweden. The collection thoroughly documents Pass's career at the Royal Institute of Technology in Stockholm, Sweden, the Urban Development Corporation in New York, and the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development in Washington, D.C. Although the inclusive dates span from 1934 to 2001, the bulk of the collection dates from the early 1960s to the early 1980s.
The correspondence in Series 1 consists of communication between David Pass and colleagues during his time in Sweden in the 1960s and with the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development in the 1970s and 1980s. There is also correspondence related to Pass's efforts to publish his work on new towns in Sweden in the 1960s and correspondence during his time with the New York Urban Development Corporation in the early 1970s.
Series 2 contains oral histories from David Pass's work on new towns in Sweden. Pass interviewed many people involved with the development and financing of new towns, particularly Farsta and Vallingby. The conversations cover the acquisition of land, the planning of the towns, and the construction. The oral histories are numbered according to a scheme created by Pass. This series also includes unedited transcripts. The original binder labels were photocopied prior to being discarded, and the photocopies were placed with the appropriate oral histories. The transcripts are in both English and Swedish.
The research and writing files in Series 3 contain substantial documentation on new towns both in the United States and internationally. Types of documents include reports, conference papers, and publications, some of which are authored by Pass. Other documents consist of clippings and correspondence. Most of the material from the 1960s covers planning and development issues most likely used by Pass for his writing and well as in his day-to-day work at the Department of City Planning in Stockholm, Sweden. The files from the 1970s and 1980s focus more on Pass's work as an analyst for the New York Urban Development Corporation and the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development. The documents contain descriptions of United States new town development in Reston, Virginia; Los Angeles, California; Columbia, Maryland; Lysander, New York; Welfare Island, New York; and Energy New Towns in the West with the Department of Energy. There is significant correspondence with regards to the Lysander and Welfare Island developments in New York in the 1970s. The international new town developments described in the documents include towns in France, London, and Vallingby, Farsta, and Stockholm in Sweden. The conference documents include information on the International New Town Association (1983) and the League of New Community Developers. The research and conference files from the early 1980s reflect Pass's growing interest in new town computer modeling. The files are arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Series 4 contains information about Reston and the Moorings Cluster Association that Pass collected when he lived there from the 1970s to the 1990s. There are multiple publications on the regulations created by the Reston Home Owners Association, which later became the Reston Association. The regulations specifically focus on design guidelines. Also included are meeting agendas for the Reston Association as well the Moorings Cluster Association on Lake Anne where Pass lived.
Series 5 consists of images of new towns in Reston, Virginia; Columbia, Maryland; Stockholm, Sweden; and Paris, France. There are also images of New York City. The subjects include buildings, street scenes, maps, and models. Some of the slides were used in presentations and also contain charts and graphs illustrating population growth and financial projections. There are also some large ariel images of the Stockholm area. The photographs are mostly 8"x10", and the slides are standard size. The slides in box 31 are glass plate and were used with the script "New Communities for New York" in box 30, folder 2. Some of the larger photographs were placed in the oversize series.
Series 6 contains 15 reel-to-reel audiotapes with interviews conducted by Pass during his new town research in Sweden. Series 2 contains the edited and unedited transcripts.
Series 7 consists mostly of maps and plans of Farsta and other towns and cities in Sweden. There is also a large plan for Reston, Virginia, a Spanish Tourism poster, and "Vallingby and Farsta" book cover artwork. Some of the oversize New York new town files and ariel photographs of Sweden are in this series as well.
Arrangement
Organized into six series:
Series 1: Correspondence, 1960s-1980s (Box 1)
Series 2: Oral Histories, 1966-1967 (Boxes 1-5)
Series 3: Research and Writing Files, 1934-2001 (Boxes 6-29)
Series 4: Reston, 1966-1996 (Boxes 30-31)
Series 5: Photographs and Slides, 1960s-1980s (Boxes 31-32)
Series 6: Audiovisual, 1966-1967 (Boxes 33-34)
Series 7: Oversize, 1960s-1970s (Box 35)
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
The Special Collections and Archives also holds the Planned Community Archives which documents the new town of Reston, Virginia.
Index Terms
Persons:
Pass, David.
Corporate Names:
New York State Urban Development Corporation.; United States. Dept. of Housing and Urban Development.
Subjects:
City planning.; City planning--New York (State); City planning--Sweden--Stockholm.; Housing.; Housing--New York(State); Housing--Stockholm--Sweden.; New towns.; New towns--New York (State); New towns--Stockholm--Sweden.; Planned communities.; Planned communities--New York (State); Planned communities--Stockholm--Sweden.
Contents List
- Series 1: Correspondence, 1960s-1980s; (0.5 box)
  The correspondence consists of communication between David Pass and colleagues during his time in Sweden in the 1960s and with the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development in the 1970s and 1980s. There is also correspondence related to Pass's efforts to publish his work on new towns in Sweden in the 1960s and correspondence during his time with the New York Urban Development Corporation in the early 1970s.
  - Correspondence, 1960s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
    5 folders.
- Series 2: Oral Histories, 1966-1967; (4.5 boxes)
  This series contains oral histories from David Pass's work on new towns in Sweden. Pass interviewed many people involved with the development and financing of new towns, particularly Farsta and Vallingby. The conversations cover the acquisition of land, the planning of the towns, and the construction. The oral histories are numbered according to a scheme created by Pass. This series also includes unedited transcripts. The original binder labels were photocopied prior to being discarded, and the photocopies were placed with the appropriate oral histories. The transcripts are in both English and Swedish.
  - Oral Histories 50-54, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Oral Histories 43-49, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Oral Histories 39-42, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Oral Histories 33-38, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Oral Histories 27-32, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Oral Histories 22-26, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Oral Histories 17-21, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Oral Histories 6-11, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Oral Histories 1-5, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Oral Histories 61-62, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Oral Histories 55-60, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Oral Histories, Index, ca. 1966 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Oral Histories, Contacts before February 1966 and List of Participants (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Oral Histories, Interview Correspondence and Notes, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Oral Histories 11-21, Unedited Interviews, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
    2 folders.
  - Oral Histories 22-32, Unedited Interviews, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Oral Histories 22-32, Unedited Interviews, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Oral Histories 60-62, Unedited Interviews, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Oral Histories 1-10, Unedited Interviews, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Oral Histories 33-46, Unedited Interviews, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
  - Oral Histories 47-59, Unedited Interviews, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
    2 folders
- Series 3: Research and Writing Files, 1931-2001; (24 boxes)
  This series contains substantial documentation on new towns both in the United States and internationally. Types of documents include reports, conference papers, and publications, some of which are authored by Pass. Other documents consist of clippings and correspondence. Most of the material from the 1960s covers planning and development issues most likely used by Pass for his writing and well as in his day-to-day work at the Department of City Planning in Stockholm, Sweden. The files from the 1970s and 1980s focus more on Pass's work as an analyst for the New York Urban Development Corporation and the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development. The files are arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - California New Town Files, 1960s-1970s (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
  - David Pass Publications, 1960s-1980s (Box 6, Folder 5-7)
    3 folders.
  - David Pass Publications, Vallingby and Farsta - From Idea to Reality, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous New Town Files, 1960s-1970s (Box 7, Folder 2-6)
  - Miscellaneous New Town Files, 1960s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 1-6)
    6 folders.
  - Miscellaneous New Town Files, 1960s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 1-6)
  - Miscellaneous New Town Files, 1960s-1970s (Box 10, Folder 1-6)
  - Miscellaneous New Town Files, 1960s-1970s (Box 11, Folder 1-4)
    4 folders.
  - New York New Town Files, 1960s-1970s (Box 11, Folder 5-7)
  - New York New Town Files, 1960s-1970s (Box 12, Folder 1-7)
    7 folders.
  - New York New Town Files, 1960s-1970s (Box 13, Folder 1-6)
  - New York New Town Files, 1960s-1970s (Box 14, Folder 1-5)
  - New York New Town Files, AIP Environmental Quality, 1970-1973 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - New York New Town Files, Columbia Process Workshop, 1971 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - New York New Town Files, Columbia University Seminar, 1971 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - New York New Town Files, DEC Institute on Man and Environment, 1972 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - New York New Town Files, Lysander Cash Flow, 1970 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - New York New Town Files, Practicing Law Institute, 1971 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Paris New Town Files, 1971-1972 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Planning and Development in the Greater Stockholm Area Draft, August 1967 (Box 15, Folder 5-6)
  - Planning and Development in the Greater Stockholm Area Draft, 1968 (Box 15, Folder 7-8)
  - Planning and Development in the Greater Stockholm Area Draft, 1968 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Project Notes from California and Early Notes from Sweden, 1964 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Research Files, 1960s-1980s (Box 16, Folder 3-6)
  - Research Files, 1960s-1980s (Box 17, Folder 1-5)
  - Research Files, 1960s-1980s (Box 18, Folder 1-6)
  - Research Files, 1960s-1980s (Box 19, Folder 1-6)
  - Research Files, 1960s-1980s (Box 20, Folder 1-5)
  - Sweden New Town Files, 1960s-1970s (Box 20, Folder 6-7)
  - Sweden New Town Files, 1960s-1970s (Box 21, Folder 1-6)
  - Sweden New Town Files, 1960s-1970s (Box 22, Folder 1-6)
  - Sweden New Town Files, 1960s-1970s (Box 23, Folder 1-6)
  - Sweden New Town Files, 1960s-1970s (Box 24, Folder 1-6)
  - Sweden New Town Files, 1960s-1970s (Box 25, Folder 1-6)
  - Sweden New Town Files, 1960s-1970s (Box 26, Folder 1-5)
  - Sweden New Town Files, 1960s-1970s (Box 27, Folder 1-3)
  - United States Department of Housing and Urban Development New Town Files, 1960s-1970s (Box 27, Folder 4-6)
  - Vallingby and Farsta Research Files, 1965 (Box 28, Folder 1-2)
  - Vallingby and Farsta Research Files, 1960s (Box 28, Folder 3-6)
  - Vallingby and Farsta Draft, February 1968 (Box 29, Folder 1-2)
- Series 4: Reston, 1966-1996; (1.5 boxes)
  Series 4 contains information about Reston and the Moorings Cluster Association that Pass collected when he lived there from the 1970s to the 1990s.
  - Clippings and Community Information, 1966-1982 (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Moorings Cluster Association, 1976-1996 (Box 30, Folder 2-4)
  - Reston Association, 1987-1992 (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - Reston Community Association, 1975 (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - Reston Home Owners Association, 1960s-1986 (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - Reston Community Association, 1981-1984 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Reston Information, 1973-1982 (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Reston Recreation, 1980s (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - Swedish Institute for Business Development Tour, 1982 (Box 31, Folder 4)
- Series 5: Photographs and Slides, 1960s-1970s; (1.5 boxes)
  This series consists of images of new towns in Reston, Virginia; Columbia, Maryland; Stockholm, Sweden; and Paris, France. There are also images of New York City. The subjects include buildings, street scenes, maps, and models. Some of the slides were used in presentations and also contain charts and graphs illustrating population growth and financial projections. There are also some large ariel images of the Stockholm area. The photographs are mostly 8"x10", and the slides are standard size. The slides in box 31 are glass plate and were used with the script "New Communities for New York" in box 30, folder 2. Some of the larger photographs were placed in the oversize series.
  - Photographs and Slides, 1960s-1970s (Box 31, Folder 5-6)
  - Slides, New Communities for New York, 1971 (Box 32)
- Series 6: Audiovisual, 1966-1967; (2 boxes)
  This series contains 15 reel-to-reel audiotapes with interviews conducted by Pass during his new town research in Sweden. Series 2 contains the edited and unedited transcripts.
  - Oral Histories, 1966-1967 (Box 33)
  - Oral Histories, 1966-1967 (Box 34)
- Series 7: Oversize, 1960s-1970s; (1 box)
  This series consists mostly of maps and plans of Farsta and other towns and cities in Sweden. There is also a large plan for Reston, Virginia, a Spanish Tourism poster, and "Vallingby and Farsta" book cover artwork. Some of the oversize New York new town files and ariel photographs of Sweden and are in this series as well.
  - Maps, Plans, and Photographs, 1960s-1970s (Oversize 35)
  - Maps and Plans, 1960s-1970s (Oversize MC)
    Placed in the mapcase "Miscellaneous" drawer in a folder labeled "Pass Papers".